This is about a hidden corner of the labor market.
سنتحدث عن الجانب المخفي من سوق العمل.
It's the world of people who need to work ultra-flexibly,
انه عالم الأشخاص الذين يحتاجون للعمل بمرونة فائقة،
if they're to work at all.
هذا إن كانوا قادرين على العمل أصلا.
So think, for instance,
تخيلوا، على سبيل المثال،
of someone who has a recurring but unpredictable medical condition,
شخصا مصاب بمرض مُزمن لا يمكن التنبؤ به،
or somebody who's caring for a dependent adult,
أو شخص عليه الاهتمام بشخص بالغ من ذوي الإعاقة
or a parent with complex child care needs.
او أبوين لطفل بحاجة لعناية خاصة.
Their availability for work can be such that it's,
ستكون قابليتهم للعمل كالتالي،
"A few hours today.
" ساعات قليلة باليوم.
Maybe I can work tomorrow, but I don't know if and when yet."
من الممكن أن اعمل غداً، لكن لا اعلم بالتحديد متى وإن كان بإمكاني ذلك."
And it's extraordinarily difficult for these people
وبالنسبة لهؤلاء الأشخاص إيجاد عمل هم في أمس الحاجة إليه
to find the work that they so often need very badly.
يعابر أمرا بالغ الصعوبة.
Which is a tragedy because there are employers
وهذا أمر مؤسف لأن هناك أرباب عمل
who can use pools of very flexible local people
يمكنهم استخدام مجموعات من الأشخاص المحليين المرنين للغاية
booked completely ad hoc around when that person wants to work.
والمنشأة فقط للعمل عندما يريد ذلك الشخص أن يعمل.
Imagine that you run a cafe.
تخيلوا أنكم تُديرون مقهى،
It's mid-morning, the place is filling up.
وأنكم فى منتصف النهار والمكان مُزدحم للغاية.
You're going to have a busy lunchtime rush.
سيكون لديكم فترة غداء جد مزدحمة.
If you could get two extra workers for 90 minutes
إذا كان بإمكانكم توظيف عاملين إضافيين لـ90 دقيقة
to start in an hour's time,
ليبدءوا العمل حلال ساعة من الآن،
you'd do it, but they'd have to be reliable, inducted in how your cafe works.
ستفعلونها، ولكن يجب أن يكونوا محل ثقة وعلى دراية بكيفية إدارة مقهاكم.
They'd have to be available at very competitive rates.
يجب أن يكونوا مُتاحين بأسعار تنافسية للغاية.
They'd have to be bookable in about the next minute.
و يجب أن يكونوا مستعدين للعمل فى الدقيقة التالية.
In reality, no recruitment agency wants to handle that sort of business,
فى الحقيقة، لا توجد وكالة توظيف تَوَد الاهتمام بمثل هذه الأعمال،
so you are going to muddle by, understaffed.
وبالتالي ستتدبرون أموركم بالموظفين المتوفرين.
And it's not just caterers, it's hoteliers, it's retailers,
ولا ينطبق هذا على الممونين فقط، بل وأصحاب الفنادق، وتجار التجزئة،
it's anyone who provides services to the public or businesses.
إنه ينطبق على أي شخص يقدم خدمات للعموم أو للتجار.
There's all sorts of organizations that can use these pools of very flexible people,
هناك الكثير من المنظمات التي يمكنها استخدام مجموعات العمال المرنين تلك.
possibly already once they've been inducted.
التي قد تكون تشكلت بالفعل.
At this level of the labor market,
عند هذا المستوى من سوق العمل،
what you need is a marketplace for spare hours.
ما تحتاجون إليه هو سوق عمل لساعات الفراغ.
They do exist. Here's how they work.
إنها موجودة. وهذه طريقة عملها.
So in this example, a distribution company has said,
على سبيل المثال، أعلنت شركة توزيع،
we've got a rush order that we've got to get out of the warehouse tomorrow morning.
لدينا طلبية عاجلة علينا إعدادها للخروج من المستودع غدا صباحا.
Show us everyone who's available.
أرونا كل شخص يمكنه القيام بالعمل.
It's found 31 workers.
لقد وجدت 31 عامل.
Everybody on this screen is genuinely available at those specific hours tomorrow.
كل واحد في هذه الشاشة قادر على العمل في تلك الساعات بالذات غدا.
They're all contactable in time for this booking.
يمكن الاتصال بهم جميعا في الوقت المناسب لحجزهم.
They've all defined the terms on which they will accept bookings.
لقد حددوا جميعا الشروط التي يقبلون العمل بها.
And this booking is within all the parameters for each individual.
ويبقى هذا الحجز في حدود المعايير العامة لكل فرد.
And they would all be legally compliant by doing this booking.
وبقيامهم بهذا الحجز يكونون جميعا متوافقين مع القانون.
Of course, they're all trained to work in warehouses.
وبالطبع، هم جميعا مكونين في العمل بالمستودعات.
You can select as many of them as you want.
يمكنكم انتقاء أكبر عدد منهم كما تريدون.
They're from multiple agencies.
قادمين من وكالات متعددة.
It's calculated the charge rate for each person for this specific booking.
وقد قامت بحساب سعر التكلفة لكل شخص مقابل هذ الحجز بالذات.
And it's monitoring their reliability.
وراقبت كفاءتهم.
The people on the top row are the provenly reliable ones.
ومن المؤكد بأن أولئك المتواجدين بالصف العلوي هم الأكثر كفاءة.
They're likely to be more expensive.
وهم على الأرجح أكثر تكلفة.
In an alternative view of this pool of local, very flexible people,
وفي نظرة مختلفة لهذه المجموعة المحلية، أو الأشخاص المرنين،
here's a market research company,
هناك شركة أبحاث السوق
and it's inducted maybe 25 local people in how to do street interviewing.
قامت بتكوين 25 من السكان المحليين في كيفية إجراء مقابلات بالشارع.
And they've got a new campaign. They want to run it next week.
وعليها القيام بحملة جديدة. وذلك بالأسبوع المقبل.
And they're looking at how many of the people they've inducted
وهم يتحققون من عدد الأشخاص القادرين على القيام بذلك
are available each hour next week.
من بين الذين كونوهم لكل ساعة في الأسبوع المقبل.
And they'll then decide when to do their street interviews.
وسيقرروا عندها موعد القيام بتلك المقابلات.
But is there more that could be done
ولكن هل من الممكن القيام بالمزيد
for this corner of the labor market?
لهذا الجانب من سوق العمل؟
Because right now there are so many people
لأنه هناك الكثير من الناس الآن
who need whatever economic opportunity they can get.
بحاجة للحصول على أي فرصة اقتصادية مهما كانت.
Let's make it personal.
دعونا نجعل الأمر شخصي.
Imagine that a young woman -- base of the economic pyramid,
تخيلوا امرأة شابه - قاعدة الهرم الاقتصادي،
very little prospect of getting a job --
احتمال ضئيل جداً للحصول على وظيفة-
what economic activity could she theoretically engage in?
نظرياً ما هو النشاط الاقتصادي الذي يمكنها الانخراط فيه؟
Well, she might be willing to work odd hours
قد تكون مستعدة للعمل خلال ساعات غريبة
in a call center, in a reception area, in a mail room.
في مركز الاتصال، في فضاء الاستقبال، في مكتب البريد.
She may be interested in providing local services to her community:
قد تكون مهتمة في تقديم خدمات محلية لمجتمعها المحلي :
babysitting, local deliveries, pet care.
مجالسة الأطفال، والتسليم المحلي، والعناية بالحيوانات الأليفة.
She may have possessions that she would like to trade
قد يكون لديها ممتلكات ترغب باستبدالها
at times she doesn't need them.
عندما لا تكون بحاجة إليها.
So she might have a sofa bed in her front room that she would like to let out.
قد يكون لديها أريكة-سرير بغرفتها ترغب في التخلي عليها.
She might have a bike, a video games console she only uses occasionally.
قد يكون لديها دراجة، ولعبة إلكترونية لا تستخدمها إلا أحيانا.
And you're probably thinking -- because you're all very web-aware --
وربما أنتم تفكرون - لأنكم تعرفون الأنترنت -
yes, and we're in the era of collaborative consumption,
ولأننا بعصر الاستهلاك التعاوني،
so she can go online and do all this.
يمكنها استخدام شبكة الإنترنت للقيام بكل ذلك.
She can go to Airbnb to list her sofa bed,
يمكنها عرض أريكة-سرير خاصتها على موقع أيربنب ،
she can go to TaskRabbit.com and say, "I want to do local deliveries," and so on.
أو موقع تسكرابيت وتقول، "أود القيام بعمليات التسليم المحلي"، وهلم جرا.
These are good sites, but I believe we can go a step further.
إنها مواقع جيدة، ولكن أعتقد أنه يمكننا الذهاب أبعد من ذلك.
And the key to that is a philosophy that we call modern markets for all.
والمفتاح لذلك هي الفلسفة التي نسميها بالأسواق الحديثة للجميع.
Markets have changed beyond recognition in the last 20 years,
لقد تغيرت الأسواق بشكل جذري في السنوات 20 الأخيرة،
but only for organizations at the top of the economy.
ولكن فقط للمنظمات المهيمنة على الاقتصاد.
If you're a Wall Street trader, you now take it for granted
إذا كنت مضارب بوول ستريت، تعتبر بيع الأصول المالية الخاصة بك
that you sell your financial assets in a system of markets
في نظام الأسواق أمرا مفروغا منه
that identifies the most profitable opportunities for you in real time,
لأنه يحدد لك الفرص الأكثر ربحية في الوقت الحقيقي،
executes on that in microseconds within the boundaries you've set.
وينفذها في أجزاء من الثانية حسب الحدود التي حددتها.
It analyzes supply and demand and pricing
ويحلل العرض والطلب والتسعير
and tells you where your next wave of opportunities are coming from.
ويخبرك من أين ستأتي فرصتك القادمة.
It manages counterparty risk in incredibly sophisticated ways.
ويدير مخاطر تخلف الطرف الآخر عن الإلتزام بطرق جد معقدة.
It's all extremely low overhead.
وجميع النفقات العامة جد منخفضة.
What have we gained at the bottom of the economy
ما الذي ربحناه نحن في الجزء السفلي من الاقتصاد
in terms of markets in the last 20 years?
فيما يتعلق بالأسواق في السنوات ال 20 الماضية؟
Basically classified adverts with a search facility.
بشكل أساسي، إعلانات مصنفة سهل البحث عنها.
So why do we have this disparity
لماذا لدينا هذا التفاوت
between these incredibly sophisticated markets at the top of the economy
بين الأسواق المتطورة بشكل لا يصدق في الجزء العلوي من الاقتصاد
that are increasingly sucking more and more activity and resource
والتي تمص أكثر فأكثر كل الأنشطة والموارد
out of the main economy into this rarefied level of trading,
الاقتصادية الرئيسية بهذا المستوى النادر من التداول،
and what the rest of us have?
وما الذي يبقى لنا؟
A modern market is more than a website;
السوق الحديثة هي أكثر من مجرد موقع على الإنترنت؛
it's a web of interoperable marketplaces,
إنها كشبكة من الأسواق القابلة للتشغيل المتبادل،
back office mechanisms, regulatory regimes,
كآليات المكتب الخلفي، كأنظمة تنظيمية،
settlement mechanisms, liquidity sources and so on.
كآليات استقرار، وكمصادر للسيولة وهلم جرا.
And when a Wall Street trader comes into work in the morning,
وعندما يأتي مضارب وول ستريت للعمل صباحا،
she does not write a listing for every financial derivative she wants to sell today
فإنها لن تكتب قائمة بكل المشتقات المالية التي تود أن تبيعها اليوم
and then post that listing on multiple websites
ثم تنشرها على مواقع متعددة
and wait for potential buyers to get in touch
وتنتظر مشترين محتملين للاتصال بها
and start negotiating the terms on which she might trade.
لتبدء بعدها بالتفاوض حول الشروط البيع.
In the early days of this modern markets technology,
في بدايات هذه التكنولوجيا الحديثة في الأسواق،
the financial institutions worked out
عملت المؤسسات المالية على إيجاد
how they could leverage their buying power, their back office processes,
طريقة تستغل بها قدرتها الشرائية وعمليات مكتبها الخلفي،
their relationships, their networks
علاقاتها، وشبكاتها
to shape these new markets that would create all this new activity.
ولإنشاء هذه الأسواق الجديدة التي ستخلق كل هذا النشاط الجديد.
They asked governments for supporting regulatory regimes,
طلبت من الحكومات دعمها بأنظمة تنظيمية،
and in a lot of cases they got it.
وقد حصلت عليه في أغلب الحالات.
But throughout the economy,
ولكن يوجد في الاقتصاد،
there are facilities that could likewise leverage
بنيات تحتية يمكن أن تستفيد
a new generation of markets
من جيل جديد من الأسواق
for the benefit of all of us.
لما فيه مصلحتنا جميعا.
And those facilities --
وهذه البنيات التحتية --
I'm talking about things like the mechanisms that prove our identity,
وأقصد بها أشياء كالآليات التي تثبت هويتنا،
the licensing authorities
السلطات
that know what each of us is allowed to do legally at any given time,
التي تعرف الأشياء القانونية المسموح بها لكل واحد منا في وقت معين،
the processes by which we resolve disputes through official channels.
العمليات التي يمكننا من خلالها حل النزاعات بفضل الطرق الرسمية.
These mechanisms, these facilities
هذه الآليات وهذه البنيات التحتية
are not in the gift of Craigslist or Gumtree or Yahoo,
ليست هدية مقدمة من كريغزليست أو جومتري أو ياهو،
they're controlled by the state.
بل إنها تحت سيطرة الدولة.
And the policymakers who sit on top of them
أما صناع القرار المتربعين فوقهم،
are, I suggest, simply not thinking about how those facilities could be used
في رأيي، لا يفكرون بالطريقة التي يمكن أن تستخدم بها تلك البنيات التحتية
to underpin a whole new era of markets.
لتشكل أساسا لحقبة جديدة بالكامل من الأسواق.
Like everyone else, those policymakers are taking it for granted
وكأي شخص آخر، يسلم صناع القرار
that modern markets are the preserve
بأن الأسواق الجديدة هي حكر على
of organizations powerful enough to create them for themselves.
منظمات قوية بما فيه الكفاية لخلقها لوحدها.
Suppose we stopped taking that for granted.
لنفترض بأننا توقفنا عن اعتبار ذلك أمرا مسلما به.
Suppose tomorrow morning the prime minister of Britain or the president of the U.S.,
لنفترض بأنه استيقظ غدا صباحا رئيس وزراء بريطانيا
or the leader of any other developed nation,
أو الرئيس الأمريكي أو زعيم أي دولة أخرى متقدمة،
woke up and said, "I'm never going to be able to create
وقال، "لن أكون ابدأ قادرا على خلق
all the jobs I need in the current climate.
جميع فرص العمل التي أحتاجها في المناخ الحالي.
I have got to focus on whatever economic opportunity I can get to my citizens.
يجب أن أركز على الفرص الاقتصادية التي يمكن أن أخلقها للمواطنين.
And for that they have to be able to access state-of-the-art markets.
و لأجل هذا يجب أن يكونوا قادرين على الولوج لأحسن أسواق الدولة.
How do I make that happen?"
كيف يمكنني القيام بذلك؟ "
And I think I can see a few eyes rolling.
أستطيع رأيت بعض العيون التي بدأت تتساءل.
Politicians in a big, complex, sophisticated I.T. project?
سياسيين في مشروع تكنولوجي كبير ومعقد ومتطور؟
Oh, that's going to be a disaster waiting to happen.
سيكون ذلك كانتظار كارثة على وشك أن تحدث.
Not necessarily.
ليس بالضرورة.
There is a precedent for technology-enabled service
فهناك سابقة لمصالح تكنولوجية
that has been initiated by politicians in multiple countries
خلقها سياسيين في بلدان متعددة
and has been hugely successful:
وقد كانت ناجحة بشكل كبير:
national lotteries.
اليانصيب الوطني.
Let's take Britain as an example.
لنأخذ بريطانيا كمثال.
Our government didn't design the national lottery,
لم تصمم حكومتنا اليانصيب الوطنية،
it didn't fund the national lottery, it doesn't operate the national lottery.
لم تمول اليانصيب الوطني، ولم تسير اليانصيب الوطني.
It simply passed the National Lottery Act and this is what followed.
بل قامت فقط بإصدار "قانون اليانصيب الوطني"، وهذا ما جاء فيه.
This act defines what a national lottery will look like.
يُعَرِّفُ هذا القانون باليانصيب الوطنية.
It specifies certain benefits
ويُحدد بعض الامتيازات
that the state can uniquely bestow on the operators.
التي تمنحها الدولة للمتعهدين فقط.
And it puts some obligations on those operators.
وتَفرض بعض الالتزامات على أولئك المتعهدين.
In terms of spreading gambling activity to the masses,
من حيث نشر القِمَار للعامة،
this was an unqualified success.
كان ذلك نجاحا كبيرا.
But let's suppose that our aim
لكن دعونا نفترض أن هدفنا
is to bring new economic activity to the base of the pyramid.
هو أن نأتي بنشاط اقتصادي جديد لقاعدة الهرم.
Could we use the same model?
هل يمكننا استخدام نفس النموذج؟
I believe we could.
أعتقد بأنه يمكننا ذلك.
So imagine that policymakers outlined a facility.
تخيلوا أن صناع القرار خططت لبنية تحتية.
Let's call it national e-markets, NEMs for short.
فلنسميها الأسواق الإلكترونية الوطنية، واختصارا ب نيمس.
Think of it as a regulated public utility.
اعتبروها كالمرافق العامة المُقَنَّنَة.
So it's on a par with the water supply or the road network.
إنها إذا بنفس أهمية التزويد بالمياه أو شبكة الطرق.
And it's a series of markets for low-level trade
وهي عبارة عن سلسلة من الأسواق التجارية ذات مستوى منخفض
that can be fulfilled by a person or a small company.
يمكن لأي شخص أو شركة صغيرة إنشاؤها.
And government has certain benefits
ولدى الحكومة بعض الامتيازات
it can uniquely bestow on these markets.
التي يمكن أن تخص بها هذه الأسواق فقط.
It's about public spending going through these markets
والمتعلقة بالإنفاق العام من خلال هذه الأسواق
to buy public services at the local level.
لشراء الخدمات العامة على المستوى المحلي.
It's about interfacing these markets
وبربط هذه الأسواق
direct into the highest official channels in the land.
مباشرة بالقنوات الرسمية العليا بالبلاد.
It's about enshrining government's role as a publicist for these markets.
وبإرساء دور الحكومة كجهة داعمة لهذه الأسواق.
It's about deregulating some sectors
وبتحرير بعض القطاعات
so that local people can enter them.
التي يمكن للسكان المحليين من ولوجها.
So, taxi journeys might be one example.
قد تكون رحلات التاكسي واحدة من الأمثلة.
And there are certain obligations that should go with those benefits
وهناك بعض الالتزامات التي من المفروض أن ترافق تلك الفوائد
to be placed on the operators,
وتمنح للمتعهدين،
and the key one is, of course,
وأهمها، بالطبع،
that the operators pay for everything,
أن المتعهدين بدفعون مقابل كل شيء،
including all the interfacing into the public sector.
بما في ذلك جميع العلاقات مع القطاع العام.
So imagine that the operators make their return
لذا تخيلوا أن المتعهدين يحققون نسبة ربح
by building a percentage markup into each transaction.
عن كل عملية.
Imagine that there's a concession period
تخيلوا أن هناك فترة امتيازات
defined of maybe 15 years
محددة ربما في 15 سنة
in which they can take all these benefits and run with them.
يمكنهم خلالها أخذ كل تلك الفوائد وتشغيلها.
And imagine that the consortia who bid to run it are told,
وتخيلوا أن يقال للائتلاف الذي يحاول الدخول في العطاء،
whoever comes in at the lowest percentage markup on each transaction
من يقدم أقل نسبة عن كل عملية
to fund the whole thing
لتمويل كل شيء
will get the deal.
سيحصل على الصفقة.
So government then exits the frame.
لتخرج بعدها الحكومة من الصورة.
This is now in the hands of the consortium.
ويبقى الأمر عندها بين أيدي الائتلاف.
Either they are going to unlock an awful lot of economic opportunity
فإما يفتح الباب لفرص اقتصادية مذهلة وعديدة
and make a percentage on all of it
فيحقق نسبة ربح على كل ذلك
or it's all going to crash and burn,
أو أن كل شيء سينهار،
which is tough on their shareholders.
الأمر الذي يصعب تقبله من مساهميهم.
It doesn't bother the taxpayer necessarily.
وهذا لا يزعج بالضرورة دافعي الضرائب.
And there would be no constraints on alternative markets.
ولن تكون محدودة فقط بالأسواق البديلة.
So this would just be one more choice
سيكون ذلك مجرد خيار إضاقي
among millions of Internet forums.
من بين ملايين منتديات الإنترنت.
But it could be very different,
لكنه سيكون أمرا جد مختلف،
because having access to those state-backed facilities
لأن الوصول إلى تلك المرافق المدعومة من الدولة
could incentivize this consortium
قد يحفز هذا الائتلاف
to seriously invest in the service.
للاستثمار بجدية في الخدمة.
Because they would have to get a lot of these small transactions going
لأنه سيتعين عليهم القيام بالكثير من هذه العمليات الصغيرة
to start making their return.
لكي نحس بالنتيجة.
So we're talking about sectors like home hair care,
ونتحدث هنا عن قطاعات مثل الحلاقة في المنازل،
the hire of toys, farm work,
تأجير لعب الأطفال، العمل بالزراعة،
hire of clothes even, meals delivered to your door,
بل حتى تأجير الملابس، وتوصيل الوجبات إلى منزلكم،
services for tourists, home care.
وخدمات للسياح، الرعاية المنزلية.
This would be a world of very small trades, but very well-informed,
سيكون عالما من العمليات الصغيرة، ولكنها قوية الأساس،
because national e-markets will deliver data.
لأن الأسواق الإلكترونية الوطنية تقدم البيانات.
So this is a local person
فلنفترض أن هناك شخص محلي
potentially deciding whether to enter the babysitting market.
يحتمل أن يُقَرِّر ما إذا كان سيلج سوق مجالسه الأطفال.
And they might be aware that they would have to fund vetting and training
وقد يكونون على علم بأنه عليهم تمويل عمليات الفحص والتدريب
if they wanted to go into that market.
إذا كانوا يريدون ولوج تلك السوق.
They'd have to do assessment interviews with local parents
سيكون عليهم القيام بمقابلات مع الآباء المحليين
who wanted a pool of babysitters.
الذين بحاجة لمجموعة الحاضنات.
Is it worth their while?
هل يستحق الأمر كل ذلك؟
Should they be looking at other sectors?
هل عليهم أن يبحثوا في القطاعات الأخرى؟
Should they be moving to another part of the country
هل عليهم الانتقال إلى جزء آخر من البلد
where there's a shortage of babysitters?
حيث يوجد حصاص في الحاضنات؟
This kind of data can become routine.
يمكن أن يصبح هذا النوع من البيانات روتينا.
And this data can be used by investors.
ويمكن للمستثمرين استخدامها.
So if there's a problem with a shortage of babysitters in some parts of the country
بالتالي إذا كانت هناك مشكلة خصاص بالحاضنات في بعض أجزاء البلد
and the problem is nobody can afford the vetting and training,
والمشكلة هي أن لا أحد يستطيع الفرز والتدريب،
an investor can pay for it
يمكن لمستثمر أن يدفع ثمنها
and the system will tithe back the enhanced earnings of the individuals
وربما سيرد النظام الأرباح المعززة للأفراد
for maybe the next two years.
للسنتين المقبلتين.
This is a world of atomized capitalism.
إنه عالم رأسمالي مُتذرٍّ.
So it's small trades by small people,
إنها مبادلات تجارية صغيرة بين أشخاص بسطاء،
but it's very informed, safe, convenient, low-overhead and immediate.
لكنها قوية الأساس وآمنة ومريحة ومنخفضة التكلفة وفورية.
Some rough research suggests this could unlock
وتشير بعض البحوث الأولية لاحتمالية أن تنتج
around 100 million pounds' worth a day of new economic activity
حوالي 100 مليون جنيه باليوم كأنشطة اقتصادية جديدة
in a country the size of the U.K.
في بلد بحجم المملكة المتحدة.
Does that sound improbable to you?
هل يبدوا لكم هذا أمرا غير وارد؟
That's what a lot of people said about turbo trading
هذا ما قاله الكثيرين عن توربو ترادينغ
in financial exchanges 20 years ago.
في التبادلات المالية قبل 20 عاماً.
Do not underestimate the transformative power
لا نقلل من قوة التغيير
of truly modern markets.
لدى الأسواق الحديثة بحق.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)